welcome to meditating with John Verve a
key we live stream every morning at 9:30
a.m. Eastern Time with Monday's
alternating between a new lesson which
we call the Dharma day and a review of
the whole ecology practices of paya day
the previous Monday was a holiday the
Monday coming up is dharma day for
previous lessons and sits please see the
description for this video I recommend
doing the first lesson right away then
start joining us everyday and then
watching a new lesson video every
Saturday or Sunday please like this
stream increase it to view in the
YouTube algorithm at the end of every
set there is Q&A please limit the
questions to this ecology of practice
that we're all on together and it's
wonderful to be on it with all of you
together
however questions for the Q&A today
please limit them to there's ecology as
I said and for broader questions more
encompassing questions of a
philosophical or scientific or more
spiritual nature please come to my
livestream on YouTube QA every third
Friday of the month it's this Friday
June 19th at 3 p.m. Eastern Time
I believe that's everything we need to
do right now we will have some time for
questions at the end so please get
yourself into your basic posture set
your phones on do that mister and then
we will begin when I say begin begin
Shh slowly come out of your practice
trying as best you can to integrate what
you cultivated in your practice with
your everyday consciousness cognition
character and communitas perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
okay so we have some time for some
questions taequan Soho has asked when I
meditate by myself there's a need to
check the time is almost fear-based
thoughts so I'm wondering what the fear
is the fear that your timer is not gonna
go off appear that you're wasting your
time doing this practice there could be
two different fears for the first one
the thing you do is and it sounds kind
of silly but it works get your timer
don't be meditating set it for 10
minutes just sit there goes up do it
again and again and again and again and
again so that you know I know I don't
mean the intellectual or reflective part
of you but the more primitive part of
your brain knows because your limbic
system learns a much slower rate than
your cortex and you have to do basically
a lot of training over and over and over
again I just know si si si si si si si
si si if it's resistance that's because
you're trying to get out of the
meditation that you need to apply the
five factors of inquiring mindfulness
you need to realize that that it
meditate immediately on the resistance
in your means you're already meditating
and you really need to work on
cultivating the Buddha the Dharma and
the Sangha to build up the inner boot of
the momentum also can you taste any
sense of being centered calm at peace in
yourself that in contrast to the part
that serve nervous and anxious
and can you bring that into more
awareness and nurture it with your
attention if it's that you feel that
you're somehow wasting your time and
meditation and there's more important
things you need to be doing
then but seriously reflect on maybe talk
to somebody about the framing you have
about befriending yourself I don't know
you and I don't want to be too intrusive
but um I know I can fall prey to this as
well so I'm speaking with experience
where I because especially the religious
bringing I was brought up and I can
confuse self-care with being selfish or
I can consider right this kind of taking
care of myself not really important
because it's not producing anything
I mean we're given all kinds of messages
that conflict with what we're doing here
and these are missed messages that are
bound up with time but if you read for
example Hans book on the scent of time
our culture has basically eroded time
it's become he calls it it's autumn eyes
and just buzzes and whiz and we have it
we've lost the capacity to linger with
things and therefore to be transformed
by touching their depths so you might
also want to take a look at some of the
work that's being done on the cultural
cognitive grammar surrounding time again
I don't know the particulars and I'm
trying to answer many different
possibilities at once and give you sort
of an overall integrated way of
responding here the time timer will not
go off or fear of being lost and avoid
okay so the first one is like I said
practice that that was another question
from time one so practice just show over
and over and I mean ad nauseam over and
over again the timer works it works it
works it works right and then a fear of
being lost and avoid have you
experienced the void
I'm not sure I'm not I'm not being
facetious I mean what is your fear of
are you imagining something then
remember to not confuse your imagination
of something with the thinking you step
back and look at the imagery and feel
how your body what your mind about
you're doing a look at no imagining
imagining and not doesn't matter that
you're imagining the void
you're imagining take a look at it oh if
you've had moments perhaps you've been
practicing for a long time where that
narrative voice drops way and you have
the silence yes that can initially be
startling and what you need to do is
trust it's a kind of faith here you need
to trust the traditions when they tell
you that if you keep going that this
goes it does an aspect shift it flips it
goes from being right to a realization
of the opposite so try to taste through
your day the fever hunger of that of our
constantly feeding that self-referential
talking might have just keep consuming
words and stories it's our moral and
what it's like so that's what the amount
of means blowing out the candle right
but it's like when that fever hunger
goes away this should go to' but also
late lets you have to trust the
tradition when it says that that will
right you'll get an aspect shift the
fundamental inversion now there's one
important caution perhaps you've
experienced trauma and this is coming up
and the fear of the void is the fear of
that of a dissociation then you need to
perhaps talk to somebody with
professional expertise about that and
maybe slow down this practice until that
tendency towards dissociation is more
properly therapeutically addressed I've
tried to give us comprehensive answer as
I can please forgive me I'm on I can
speak out of what I know in the
experience of teaching in of other
people have done this but everybody also
has their own idiosyncratic situation
and so I hope I helped Dimitar what does
surrendering to the experience
practically mean in terms you use in
this course a lot vocal people
emphasized the importance of surrender
and psychedelic trip and it seems to me
like some kind of surrender is important
in order to gain the systematic insight
so for me I don't use the term surrender
a lot and that's that that's partially
because of my own religious upbringing
in the way it harmed me but also also do
my ignorance of Islam which means of
course to surrender but I I've got a
much deeper understanding I think of
what you're talking about
especially from on Taoism and also from
the Buddhist practices also from the
Neoplatonic tradition the way I
understand it is and this has to do with
the cognitive science of the kind of
mode you need to be in in order to have
an insight if you try to force it inside
if you're trying to have an insight you
won't have one in fact that very sort of
tight hard focus and grasping will
thwart what you have to do is you have
to let go of that you have to move out
of modal confusion and to move into the
being mode and then what we're doing is
we are trying to sensitize ourselves and
afford the fact that our minds are
ultimately dynamically self-organizing
and we are trying to let so we do all
this plan it but we forget that all of
our planning actually depends on our
moment-to-moment ability to cope with
situations and dynamically self organize
and adjust and then below the coping
what grounds the coping is how we're
actually dynamically coupled to the
world and how that can go go bad and
reciprocal narrowing or open up and
reciprocal opening and then ultimately
below the coupling is is that the kind
of conformity that that there's there
there are principles at work within that
are also at work without principles and
patterns and so surrendering means to
stop trying to run the whole show from
the planning mode to recognize and
accept that ok now is the time where I
cope and then below that the coping
depends on now is a time in which I
allow myself to be dynamically coupled
to the world etc and so that's how I
understand the surrendering in this
process ultimately to acknowledge and
recognize recognize acknowledge and
recognize the fact that most of my
cognition is not ultimately in my
planning although it gets a lot of my
attention because that planning depends
on the coping which depends on the
coupling which ultimately depends on a
deep kind of ontological conformity and
the surrendering is a deep kind of
acknowledge a lived enacted recognition
of that I hope that was a hopeful answer
here a hi Kara here Crowther I've been
relisting to the routing list and I
noticed it's much easier to do reading
what really what I'm listening to you
going through it that's helped me notice
that my inner coach doesn't have much
authority and so monkey mind comes up
big time how can I increase the
authority without being punishing you
have to cultivate you Buddha you have to
celebrate it more you have to note keep
a journal in the moments and this sounds
self aggrandizing and right and of
course that's why all the hero myths are
paired with hubris myths but right you
can there's there there's vices of
excess and there's vices of deficit as
Aristotle would say you're pointing to
you need help with literally
encouragement so you need to more
actively water your Buddhas celebrate
your Buddha perhaps read more stories of
the historical Buddha right try and
notice moon or what I saw I sort I
apologize there shouldn't be
presumptuous prompts your Christian
perhaps your inner sage is Jesus Christ
perhaps your Taoist and right it's more
loud say I don't want to be presumptuous
but that's what I mean by the inner
Buddha right and so if you're that's
your sage isn't the historical Buddha as
an exemplar whoever you're spend more
time in the presence by a text obviously
of the historical model your exemplar
and also keep a journal collect moments
of when you were mindful when you are
insightful really try it and when that
happens try to remember and relive it
will experience it what does it feel
like in your mind and body when you're
your inner Buddha is presencing itself
you you need to give that right more
rounded presence in your mind and body
so that your inner coach can actually be
the the voice through which that Buddha
nature can come to speak to you the job
my job is to make myself obsolete my job
is to be a teacher that awakens within
you your inner teacher taku and so ho
when I meditate no sorry Matthew
McCready I already answered tonkoon's
question Matthew McCready you have
mentioned along the lines that spiritual
practices shouldn't be done for reasons
such as special powers gaining more
power in the world being content getting
rid of negative and all emotions like a
stone Buddha or making us feel unique
and special what is right motivation
viable for why we personally need to
transform our awakening using these
practices yeah so the right motivation
is right motivation well what I want to
say I'm afraid of it being misheard or
miss framed as a special power the right
motivation is the cultivation of wisdom
which is the Buddhist said you know no
matter where you put your cup in the
ocean it has the same taste right salt
well no matter where you put your cup in
the ocean of my teaching it has the same
flavor freedom and freedom from and
freedom to freedom
shouldn't be pursued at its own sake
it's it's it's an instrumental good
what's the good well we want to meet we
want to be as free as we can for
ourselves and for each other equally for
ourselves and for each other we want to
be as free from self-deception
as possible self-deception
self-destructive and we want to be free
to flourish which means we want to
enhance as much as we can for ourselves
and for others equally the ability to be
connected that that dynamic coupling
mind and body connected connected to
yourself connected to each other
connected to the world so fast
what Africa we're after and this is the
you know standard Mahayana Buddhist
phrase were after the liberation of all
sentient beings and that sounds very
grand but a man's reach or let's let's
update grounding so if I quit so success
a person's reach should exceed their
grasp or what is a heaven for so right
we are trying in the end to bring a kind
of fullness of being to as many beings
as possible excellent questions really
really excellent questions so thank you
everyone for joining this sang it is
nurturing and nourishing and I deeply
appreciate it
I appreciate everything that's happening
in it I want to thank my dear friend and
technomage Omar that's making everything
happen my beloved son Jason was always
behind the scenes taking care of things
that need to be taken care of coping as
things unexpectedly come up please
subscribe to the channel to be notified
of the next video you'll also find links
to the lecture series awakening from the
meeting crisis and the dialogo series
voices with reveille key in which these
themes and many others are explored in
depth and set within a much more
comprehensive way of life invite others
who might benefit by sharing this series
so it can help as many people as
possible with it
brett is usually here pleasure of doubt
and he
we'll help guide people Shepherd people
into the discord server there is a link
in the description well you will find
people have sat on perhaps doing Lexi o
other group practices a much more
expensive community I'm on there every
second Monday doing Q&A many of the
people that are on voices with rebecky
are they're doing Q&A it's a wonderful
vital and vibrant community it is where
a culture of Awakening right is perhaps
being born please remember that we are
doing this every weekday morning at 9:30
Eastern Time
please remember that continuity of
practice is more important than the
sheer quantity of practice there is no
enemy worse than your own mind and body
there is no friend no ally no true
companion on the path better than your
own mind and body relax
unto yourself and to each other I'll see
you tomorrow
take good care